Leland C. Wyman papers, 1908-1985 (bulk 1930-1980)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Leland C. Wyman papers 1908-1985 (bulk 1930-1980)
MS 441
Wyman, Leland Clifton, 1897-
Papers, 1908-1985, bulk 1930-1980. This collection is comprised of Leland C. Wyman’s interests, both personal and professional. The bulk is made up of personal and professional correspondence, lecture note cards, and publications. His professional files reflect both his careers as a biologist and an anthropologist.
3.5 linear ft.
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Leland Clifton Wyman was born in 1897 Livermore Falls, Maine. He got his bachelor’s degree from Bowdoin College in 1918 and his Ph. D. degree from Harvard in 1922. He taught experimental and theoretical physiology, sociology, anthropology, American Indian art, and Asiatic art at the Boston College of Liberal Arts. He also directed research work on Navajo ethnology at the Department of Anthropology, University of New Mexico. From 1942 to 1946 he served as chairman of the Division of Medical Sciences at Boston University. He spent 40 summers conducting research in the American southwest establishing him as one of the leaders on Navajo research. He was an author of numerous publications in the fields of biology and anthropology. For various years he was the curator of archives at the Museum of Northern Arizona and research associate at the Museum of Navajo Ceremonial Art. As part of his research and personal interests he traveled to Asia, Africa, Middle East, and Europe. He died in 1988.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into two series.
Series I: Personal,
Series II: Professional,
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains personal and professional materials relating to the life and career of Leland C. Wyman. The bulk of the personal series includes correspondence to and from Wyman as well as correspondence between others. General files relating to his personal life include his drawings and sketches and other materials collected by him including a song book, theatre programs, and newspaper clippings. Scrapbooks detail information on sports programs and materials on or about Livermore Falls and Bowdoin College. The professional series includes correspondence as well as general files on museum collections and his teaching files. The collection also contains a large amount of his index card lecture notes. Also present in the collection are numerous essays and publications by Leland Wyman, spanning over 60 years.
Access Terms
Wyman, Leland Clifton, 1897-1988
Navajo Indians
Indians of North America
Biology
Single Cell Research Foundation
Container List
- Series I: Personal, 1908-1985
  - Subseries I: Correspondenceca. 1908-1985
    This subseries is arranged chronologically. It contains correspondence between Leland C. Wyman with his family and friends. It is organized alphabetically and chronologically.
    - Correspondence, 1900-1940s (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence1965-1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence 1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence 1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence 1979-1981 1985 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence-Season’s Greetings 1956-1972 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence-Season’s Greetings, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence-Season’s Greetings, 1977-1980; 1983 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Subseries II: Generalca. 1908-1985
    This subseries is arranged alphabetically. It contains arts and crafts from childhood to his sketches for studying human anatomy, Bowdoin College files, calendars and schedules, childhood museum catalogue, essays, White Star ephemera, invitations and announcements, materials from his interest on magic and spiritual matters, newspaper clippings, notebooks, address book, song book, and theater programs from Europe.
    - Arts and Crafts-Drawings and sketches of animals and nature (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Arts and Crafts-Drawings and sketches of geography and geology (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Arts and Crafts-Scientific drawings of the human body (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Arts and Crafts-Drawings and sketches of human subjects (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Arts and Crafts-Drawings and sketches of objects (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Bowdoin College files (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Calendars and schedules (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Childhood museum catalogue (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Essays (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - First trip to Europe White Star ephemera (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Invitations and announcements (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Magic and spiritual (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Magic-Newspaper clippings (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Notebooks and address book (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Song book (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Theater programs from Europe (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Subseries III: Scrapbooksca. 1908-1940s
    This series is arranged alphabetically. It contains scrapbooks dedicated to Livermore Falls, Bowdoin College, and college sports.
    - Scrapbook (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Scrapbook Livermore Falls and Bowdoin College (Box 5, Box 2)
    - Scrapbook-Programs of college sports events (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Series II: Professional, 1908-1985
  - Correspondence, 19201970
    This series is arranged chronologically and alphabetically. It contains the professional correspondence of Leland C. Wyman.
    - Correspondence, 1920s; 1930s (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1940 October-1945 October (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1945 November-1949 November (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1950s (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1960s (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1970-1980 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence-Boston University MOnetary appointments, 1922-1964 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence-Donations, loans, and appraisal of collections, ca 1937-1979 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence-Exhibits and collections, ca 1953-1979 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence-Exhibit, The Art of Book in the East, ca 1954-1958 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence-Exhibits Islamic and Persian Art, ca 1958-1963 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence-Faculty and student research, 1937-1959 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence-Publications and reviews, ca 1937-1978 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence-Research on North American Indians and the southwest, 1931-1979 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence-Single Cell Research Foundation, 1954-1970 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, Undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Subseries II: General, ca. 1920-1980
    This series is arranged alphabetically. It contains Awards, recognitions, memberships, collection value, curriculum vitae, faculty and student evaluation, inventory of artifacts, invitations and announcements, journal, key to catalogue numbers of Wyman Collection, lectures and speaking engagements, miscellaneous, museum programs, flyers, catalogues, notes for exhibits, outlines, teaching materials, travel logs and itineraries.
    - Awards, recognitions, and memberships (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Collection value, ca. 1953-1958 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Collection value-American Indian, ca. 1960 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Collection value-Asian (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Collection value-Egyptian and African (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Collection value-Islamic, ca. 1958 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Collection value-Latin America (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Collection value-Persian and Indian, ca. 1953-1958 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - CURRICULAM VITAE and personal information, ca. 1927-1959 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Faculty and student evaluation, ca. 1948-1969 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Inventory of artifacts (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Invitations and announcements (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Journal, 1920 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Key to catalogue numbers of Wyman Collection (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Lectures and speaking engagements, 1933-1972 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Museum programs, flyers, catalogues, ca. 1954-1970 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Captions for exhibits (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Outlines (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Teaching materials (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Travel logs and itineraries (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Subseries III: Essays and publications
    This series is arranged alphabetically. It contains bibliography, essays, journal articles, newsletters, publications, and papers and publications by others.
    - Bibliography, 1922-1959; 1970 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Essays (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Journal articles (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Newsletters (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Publications, 1920s (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Publications, 1930s (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Publications, 1940s (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Publications, 1950s (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Publications, 1960s-1970s (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Papers and publications by others, ca 1912-1968 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Subseries 4: Lecture note cards
    Lecture note cards from his teaching days at Boston University on the topics of American Indians, Chinese, Japanese, and Indian culture and art.
    - Lecture note cards-American Indians (Box 9)
    - Lecture note cards-American Indians/China and Japan (Box 10)
    - Lecture note cards-China and Japan/India (Box 11)
    - Lecture note cards-India (Box 12)